Finding Aid for James J. Blanchard Papers, 1982-2002
Bentley Historical Library
The Press Office presented the public face for the Blanchard administration. This office coordinated press conferences, released policy statements and copies of Blanchard's speeches, arranged photo opportunities, mediated with local and state media, and generally put the best possible spin on the administration. The Press Office was the single point of fixity in the field of flux that was the Blanchard executive office. This office fell under the eye of only two directors, Rick Cole and Tom Scott, during the two gubernatorial terms. Scott was with the office almost from the outset and is largely responsible for the retention of much of the materials. He treated the Press Office as the archives of the executive office, saving newspaper clippings, press releases, speeches, audiotapes, videotapes, and photographs which document the public life of Blanchard. These materials provide the most comprehensive picture of Blanchard as politician, statesman, governor.
The Upper Peninsula Office was one of the regional offices established by the executive office to better serve a specific clientele, in this case the residents of the upper peninsula. This office brought the services of state government to the more immediate attention of upper peninsula citizens. It answered constituent correspondence, served as liaison between county officials and the state, and briefed the Governor for his trips to the upper peninsula. In short the Upper Peninsula Office provided a scaled-down version of the outreach functions offered by the executive office. Tom Baldini, director of the office, filled his post so competently that he was viewed by the executive office and citizens as the "governor" of the upper peninsula.
The Washington Office served as a clearinghouse for information on federal proposals, congressional legislation, and national policy developments. It also lobbied for the interests of the state. In pursuing these ambitious, if amorphous, interests, the Washington Office employed a staff of five to ten people over the years of Blanchard's tenure. The staff of the office worked with Blanchard, the executive office, and Michigan agency directors to develop responses to federal activity, to initiate timely communication between federal and state officials, and to arrange and conduct meetings and conferences when appropriate. Aside from the director of the Washington Office, E. Douglas Frost, who focused on budgets, taxes, and overall policy planning, each of the staff members in the office was responsible for broadly defined issues. Rosemary Freeman, who preceded Frost as office director, served as deputy director and handled issues related to training, labor, and education. James Callow was the legislative analyst charged with keeping abreast of economic and trade issues. Maura Cullen was responsible for social services, health and human services, and child welfare. Peter Kyriacopolous was the last of three analysts (Charlie Moses and Jo Ellen D'Arcy preceded him) who handled concerns related to the environment and transportation.
Governors -- Michigan.; Michigan -- Politics and government -- 1981-1990.; Governors -- Michigan.; Parades -- Michigan.; Political elections -- Michigan.; Politics and government -- Michigan.; Governors -- Michigan.; Michigan -- Politics and government -- 1981-1990.; Videotapes.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Digital audio files.; Blanchard, James J., 1942-; Democratic Party (Mich.); Michigan. Governor (1983-1991: Blanchard); Blanchard, James J., 1942-; Michigan. Governor (1983-1991: Blanchard); Blanchard, James J., 1942-; Democratic Party (Mich.); Michigan. Governor (1983-1991: Blanchard)
- Chief of Staff/Executive Assistants, 1982-1991
  The Chief of Staff/Executive Assistants, 1982-1991 series consists of 28 linear feet of materials arranged into seven subseries each focused on a staff member. These seven subseries fall into two distinct classes: Chief of Staff (F. Thomas Lewand, Phillip Jourdan, and Steve Weiss) and Executive Assistants (Nancy Austin-Schwartz, Bill Liebold, Carolyn Sparks, and Ron Thayer). The arrangement of the Chief of Staff materials follows the chronological terms of their tenure, so it roughly parallels Blanchard's first and second terms. The Lewand and Jourdan subseries cover Blanchard's first term; the Weiss subseries covers the second. As noted in the Scope and Content Note, there are no materials extant from Rick Cole's tenure as Chief of Staff. The materials of the Executive Assistants are arranged alphabetically according to staff member. This awkward melding of chronological and alphabetical arrangements was dictated by the original order of the records and by the desire to keep the materials of Chiefs of Staff and Executive Assistants in close proximity. The researcher is again cautioned that the upper echelons of the Blanchard staff did not hew to administrative taxonomies, thus there will be considerable interpenetration and overlap between subseries. The most extensive of these overlaps are noted in the folder and box listings.
  - Tom Le, 1982-1983
    The F. Thomas Lewand subseries comprises one linear foot of materials and is arranged alphabetically by type of material or office of origin. Lewand's principal concern was overseeing Blanchard's transition from candidate to governor; similar materials can be found in the Government Relations series. This transition is best covered in the Lewand subseries by the memoranda, "key decisions," and budget materials of the transition office. The memoranda are a rich source on Blanchard's thinking as policies were implemented and assessed. Other materials of interest in this subseries can be found in the personnel folders, in which aspiring job-seekers attempt to trade personal and political capital for a position on the Blanchard team.
    - Blanchard Business Council, 1982; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1982-1983; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Inaugural Committee, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Legal, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Legislative/Policy, 1982; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Michigan Fiscal Crisis Council, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Memoranda, 1982-1983; 8 folders (Box 1)
    - Personnel, 1982; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Press, 1982; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Transition Office, 1982
      (See also Government Relations Box 47)
      - Budget (Box 1)
      - Correspondence (Box 1)
      - "Key Decisions" (Box 1)
      - Memoranda, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Office Relocation (Box 1)
      - Schedules, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Phillip Jourdan, 1982-1986
    The Phillip Jourdan subseries runs six linear feet and is arranged alphabetically according to type of material: assignment tracking, correspondence, departments, memoranda, and subject files. Jourdan's assignment tracking provides a good record of issues raised in memos and letters and tracks their handling by the various executive offices. The Blanchard correspondence in Jourdan's files are copies of outgoing letters Blanchard thought significant enough to policy that Jourdan should have a copy. These runs of assignment tracking and correspondence cover the years 1983-1986; the years 1986-1990 can be found in the files of Executive Assistant, Carolyn Sparks. Evidently these files fell out of the Chief of Staff's realm after Jourdan's tenure. Also of interest are the memoranda which detail Blanchard's involvement in the daily implementation and assessment of policy during his first term. The department and subject files are arranged alphabetically by department or issue and contain reports, memos, and correspondence.
    - Assignment tracking, 1983-1986
      (See also Carolyn Sparks Box 23)
      - General description, 1983-1986 (Box 2)
      - Monthly, 1983-1985; 15 folders (Box 2)
      - Quarterly, 1985-1986; 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Daily, June 1984-October 1985; 16 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - Blanchard, 1983-1986; 7 folders (Box 3)
        (See also Carolyn Sparks Box 24; Correspondence Unit, Boxes 31-34)
      - Chronological, 1983-1986; 12 folders (Box 3)
    - Departments, 1982-1986
      - Aging, Office of Services to, 1983 (Box 3)
      - Agriculture, 1983-1985 (Box 3)
      - Attorney General, 1983 (Box 3)
      - Auditor General, 1983-1986; 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Cabinet Council on Jobs and Economic Development, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
      - Commerce, 1983-1985
        - General, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
        - Mortgage Lending/Redlining, 1985 (Box 4)
      - Corrections, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
      - Detroit Office, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
      - Education, 1983-1985
        - General, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
        - Adult Education, 1984 (Box 4)
        - Higher, 1983-1984; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Executive Office Budgets, 1983 (Box 4)
      - Labor, 1982-1985
        - General, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
        - Job Partnership Training Act, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
        - Michigan Youth Corps, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
        - Michigan Employment Security Commission, 1982-1985 (Box 4)
        - Office For Job Training, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
      - Licensing and Regulation, 1983-1984; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Management and Budget, 1983-1985; 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Mental Health, 1982-1984 (Box 5)
      - Military Affairs, 1984-1985; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Natural Resources, 1982-1984
        - General, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
        - Emergency Management Division (Berlin Farro), 1982-1983; 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Environmental Protection, 1983-1984 (Box 5)
      - Public Health, 1983 (Box 5)
      - Social Services, 1983-1984; 3 folders (Box 5)
      - State Employer, 1983-1985; 3 folders (Box 5)
      - State Police, 1986 (Box 5)
      - Transportation, 1983-1984; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Treasury, 1983-1984 (Box 5)
      - Upper Peninsula Office, 1983 (Box 5)
      - Washington Office, 1983-1984 (Box 5)
    - Memoranda
      - 1983-1986, 20 folders (Box 6)
    - Subject Files, 1982-1986
      - ACTION, 1985-1986 (Box 6)
      - Administrative Rules, 1983 (Box 6)
      - Black Associates in State Employment, 1983 (Box 6)
      - Children's Issues, 1983-1984 (Box 6)
      - Committee to Save Michigan, 1984 (Box 6)
      - Economic Development, 1983-1984 (Box 6)
      - Emergency Hunger Program, 1983; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Executive Orders, 1983-1984 (Box 6)
      - Fiscal Policy, 1983-1984 (Box 6)
      - Grand Prix (Detroit), 1983-1985 (Box 6)
      - Great Lakes Atlas, 1983 (Box 6)
      - Handicappers, 1983 (Box 6)
      - Hiring Freeze (Michigan), 1983 (Box 6)
      - Human Needs Committee, 1983 (Box 6)
      - Inc. 550, 1983 (Box 6)
      - Indian Fishing Rights, 1983-1984 (Box 6)
      - Intergovernmental Relations, 1983-1984 (Box 6)
      - Invitations, 1983-1984; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Lake County Task Force, 1983 (Box 7)
      - Legislators, 1983-1986; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Lobby Act, 1983 (Box 7)
      - Michigan Drunk Driving Task Force, 1983-1984 (Box 7)
      - Michigan Financial Crisis Council, 1983-1984; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - National Governors' Association, 1983-1986 (Box 7)
      - Oakdale Arbitration, 1983 (Box 7)
      - Oil Overcharge (LIHEAP), 1983 (Box 7)
      - PCBs, 1983 (Box 7)
      - Prosecuting Attorneys Appellate Service, 1983 (Box 7)
      - Stablex (Solid Waste), 1983-1984 (Box 7)
      - State Appellate Defenders Office, 1983 (Box 7)
      - State Building Authority, 1983-1986 (Box 7)
      - State Research Fund, 1982-1983 (Box 7)
      - Toxic Waste Cleanup, 1984 (Box 7)
      - Touche Ross (Deficit), 1985 (Box 7)
      - Wayne County Charter Commission, 1982-1983 (Box 7)
      - Wayne County Hospital, 1983 (Box 7)
      - White Pine Mine, 1985 (Box 7)
      - Women's Commission, 1986 (Box 7)
  - Steve Weiss, 1984-1991
    The Steve Weiss subseries consists of just over eight linear feet of records arranged alphabetically by type of material: budgets, departments, and topical. These document his activities both as Deputy Chief of Staff, 1986-1987, and as Chief of Staff, 1988-1990. The budget materials contain final drafts of executive budgets arranged chronologically by fiscal year. Other budget-related materials can be found in Carolyn Sparks' topical files and in the records of E. Douglas Frost in the Washington Office series. The bulk of the Weiss subseries consists of six linear feet of department files arranged alphabetically. These contain reports, briefing papers, and memoranda which the various departments wished to bring to the governor's attention during his second term. These are also a good source on Blanchard's efforts to control the various executive agencies. The last foot of material in this subseries consists of a topical file created for those issues which did not readily fit departmental categories.
    - Budgets
      (See also Washington Office Boxes 224-225)
      - 1983-1984, 1 volume (Box 7)
      - 1984-1985, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - 1985-1986, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - 1986-1987, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - 1987-1988, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - 1989-1990, 1 volume (Box 8)
        (includes notes)
      - 1990-1991, 2 volumes (Box 8)
    - Departments, 1986-1990
      - Administrative Taxonomy, 1986 (Box 9)
      - Aging, Office of Services to, 1987 (Box 9)
      - Agriculture, 1987-1990
        - General, 1987-1990; 4 folders (Box 9)
        - Gas Price Rollback, 1990 (Box 9)
      - Attorney General, 1989-1990 (Box 9)
      - Auditor General, 1989-1990 (Box 9)
      - Cabinet Councils, 1986-1990
        - Human Investment, 1988-1990; 3 folders (Box 9)
        - Human Services, 1987-1989; 5 folders (Box 9)
        - Jobs and Economic Development, 1986 (Box 9)
      - Children and Youth Services, 1989-1990 (Box 9)
      - Civil Rights, 1988-1990 (Box 10)
      - Civil Service, 1985-1990; 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Commerce, 1987-1990
        - General, 1987-1990; 5 folders (Box 10)
        - Child Care, 1989-1990 (Box 10)
        - Detroit Compact, 1989-1990 (Box 10)
        - Economic Alliance for Michigan, 1987 (Box 10)
        - Greater Grand Rapids, 1988 (Box 10)
        - Liquor Control Commission, 1988-1990; 2 folders (Box 10)
        - Michigan Housing Coordinating Council, 1990 (Box 10)
        - Michigan State Housing Development Authority, 1988-1990; 2 folders (Box 11)
        - Michigan Strategic Fund, 1987-1989; 3 folders (Box 11)
        - Neighborhood Builders Alliance, 1990 (Box 11)
        - Public Service Commission, 1988-1989 (Box 11)
        - Urban Resources Directory, 1988 (Box 11)
      - Corrections, 1987-1989; 3 folders (Box 11)
      - Drug Agencies, 1989-1990; 3 folders (Box 11)
      - Education, 1987-1990
        - General, 1989-1990 (Box 11)
        - Higher, 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 11)
        - Michigan Education Trust, 1987-1989 (Box 11)
        - School Finance Reform, 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Executive Office, 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Labor, 1986-1990
        - General, 1987-1989; 3 folders (Box 12)
        - Job Participant Training, 1988 (Box 12)
        - Michigan Employment Security Commission, 1986-1988; 2 folders (Box 12)
        - Michigan Youth Corps, 1986-1987 (Box 12)
        - Unemployment Insurance, 1988 (Box 12)
        - Workers' Compensation, 1987-1988 (Box 12)
      - Licensing and Regulation, 1986-1990
        - General, 1986-1990; 3 folders (Box 12)
        - Blue Cross/Blue Shield, 1987-1988 (Box 12)
        - Essential Insurance, 1986 (Box 12)
      - Lottery, 1986-1989; 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Management and Budget, 1986-1990
        - General, 1986-1990; 3 folders (Box 12)
        - Michigan Council for the Arts, 1986-1988 (Box 12)
      - Mental Health, 1987-1989 (Box 13)
        - General, 1987-1989; 3 folders (Box 13)
        - Advisory Council, 1988; 2 folders (Box 13)
        - Hospitals, 1988 (Box 13)
        - Traverse City Regional Hospital, 1989 (Box 13)
      - Military Affairs, 1987-1989; 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Natural Resources, 1986-1989
        - General, 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 13)
        - Acid Rain, 1988 (Box 13)
        - Champion International, 1986-1988 (Box 13)
        - Great Lakes, 1986-1989; 2 folders (Box 13)
        - Homestead, 1988-1989 (Box 13)
        - Low-Level Radioactive Waste, 1986-1988 (Box 13)
        - Quality of Life Bond, 1988-1989 (Box 13)
        - Renewable Resource Initiative, 1986-1987 (Box 13)
      - Public Health, 1986-1989
        - General, 1987-1988; 2 folders (Box 13)
        - Access to Care Task Force, 1986-1987 (Box 13)
        - AIDS, 1987-1988 (Box 13)
        - Managing Michigan's Health Care Costs, 1989 (Box 13)
      - Secretary of State, 1988 (Box 14)
      - Social Services, 1987-1989
        - General, 1987-1989; 4 folders (Box 14)
        - Housing/Homeless, 1987-1988; 2 folders (Box 14)
        - Juvenile Justice, 1987-1988 (Box 14)
      - State Employer, 1987-1988; 2 folders (Box 14)
      - State Police, 1987-1990; 3 folders (Box 14)
      - Substance Abuse Services, 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Transportation, 1986-1990
        - General, 1986-1990; 3 folders (Box 14)
        - Package Proposal, 1987 (Box 14)
        - Speed Limit, 1987 (Box 14)
      - Treasury, 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Topical, 1986-1991
      - Business Climate, 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Campaign 86, Accomplishments, 1986 (Box 15)
      - Detroit, 1987-1988; 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Indian Affairs, 1987-1988 (Box 15)
      - Memoranda, 1987-1988 (Box 15)
      - Political Information, 1988 (Box 15)
      - Rent Control, 1988 (Box 15)
      - Resignations, 1990 (Box 15)
      - Scheduling, 1988 (Box 15)
      - Tourism, 1986-1988 (Box 15)
      - Transition, 1990-1991 (Box 15)
      - USA Today Interview, 1987 (Box 15)
      - Wayne County Commission, 1987-1988 (Box 15)
      - Wayne County Resident Hospital, 1987-1988 (Box 15)
  - Nancy Austin-Schwartz (Deputy Chief of Staff), 1985-1990
    The Nancy Austin-Schwartz subseries consists of two categories: departments and issues. The subseries is five linear feet long. Austin-Schwartz' responsibilities as Deputy Chief of Staff entailed overseeing both the implementation of the State of the State agenda and the external relations of the Issues department. Thus the departmental materials in her files are a rich source on how well departments met Blanchard's expectations; whether the administration was meeting departmental needs; and how to respond to specific problems. The issues files consists of an alphabetical run of issues salient to Austin-Schwartz. The most significant of these are the State of the State folders which document her post hoc assessment of the year's programs. Other State of the State materials can be found in Carolyn Sparks' files and among the Issues and Press Office series. The State of the State was the principal public address of the governor, so it should come as no surprise that materials related to it appears in many files.
    - Departments, 1985-1990
      - Aging, 1987-1989; 3 folders (Box 16)
      - Agriculture, 1985-1990; 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Cabinet Council, 1986-1990
        - Human Investment, 1986-1988 (Box 16)
        - Human Services, 1986-1990; 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Children and Youth Services, 1985-1989; 3 folders (Box 16)
      - Civil Rights, 1987-1990; 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Commerce, 1986-1990
        - General, 1986-1989; 2 folders (Box 16)
        - Child Care, 1990 (Box 16)
        - Governor's Conference on Small Business, 1988 (Box 16)
        - Michigan State Housing Development Authority, 1986-1989 (Box 16)
        - Neighborhood Builders Alliance, 1989-1990 (Box 16)
      - Corrections, 1986-1989 (Box 16)
      - Education, 1985-1990
        - General, 1985-1989; 2 folders (Box 16)
        - Choice, 1987 (Box 16)
        - Classrooms of Tomorrow, 1990 (Box 16)
        - "Making Cents for Kids,", 1987 (Box 17)
        - Preschool, 1987 (Box 17)
        - Reports, 1987-1990 (Box 17)
      - Executive Office, 1985-1987 (Box 17)
      - Human Services, 1986-1988
        - General, 1987-1988 (Box 17)
        - Children's Advocate, 1987-1988 (Box 17)
        - Disability Management, 1986-1988 (Box 17)
        - Homelessness, 1986-1988 (Box 17)
      - Labor, 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Lottery, 1988 (Box 17)
      - Management and Budget, 1986-1988 (Box 17)
      - Mental Health, 1986-1990
        - General, 1986-1990 (Box 17)
        - Northville Layoffs, 1987 (Box 17)
        - Quality Care, 1986 (Box 17)
        - Robert Wood Johnson Foundation, 1989 (Box 17)
        - Traverse City Regional Hospital, 1988-1989 (Box 17)
      - Military Affairs, 1986-1988 (Box 17)
      - Natural Resources, 1986-1990; 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Public Health, 1985-1990
        - General, 1986-1989; 2 folders (Box 17)
        - AIDS, 1985-1989; 2 folders (Box 17)
        - Health Care Costs, 1988-1989 (Box 17)
        - Indoor Radon, 1988 (Box 18)
        - Infant Mortality, 1985-1987 (Box 18)
        - Minority Issues, 1988 (Box 18)
        - Nursing Homes, 1986-1988 (Box 18)
        - Personnel, 1988-1990 (Box 18)
        - Primary Health Care, 1989 (Box 18)
      - Social Services, 1985-1990; 3 folders (Box 18)
      - Secretary of State, 1987-1989
        - General, 1987-1989 (Box 18)
        - Traffic Safety, 1987-1988; 3 folders (Box 18)
      - State Employer, 1987 (Box 18)
      - Substance Abuse Office, 1987-1989 (Box 18)
      - Transportation, 1988-1989 (Box 18)
      - Treasury, 1985-1987; 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Issues, 1985-1990
      - Blacks in Michigan, 1986-1987; 3 folders (Box 18)
      - Council of State Policy and Planning Agencies, 1988-1989; 3 folders (Box 19)
      - Crime, 1985-1987 (Box 19)
      - Disaster Relief, 1986-1987 (Box 19)
      - Drugs, 1986-1988; 3 folders (Box 19)
      - Ethnic Communities, 1987 (Box 19)
      - Great Lakes States Games, 1988 (Box 19)
      - Griffiths, Martha (Awards), 1988-1989 (Box 19)
      - Handicappers, 1985-1987 (Box 19)
      - Immigration Reform, 1987 (Box 19)
      - Juvenile Justice, 1986-1987 (Box 19)
      - Local Governance, 1986-1989; 5 folders (Box 19)
      - Michigan Association of Counties, 1986-1988; 2 folders (Box 19)
      - Midwest Governors' Conference, 1988 (Box 19)
      - National Governors' Association, 1987 (Box 19)
      - Native Americans, 1985-1988; 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Northwest-Midwest Institute, 1987-1988; 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Sesquicentennial, 1986-1988; 2 folders (Box 20)
      - State of the State, 1988-1990; 5 folders (Box 20)
        (See also Carolyn Sparks Box 26; Issues Boxes 128-129; Press Office Boxes 177-181, 187, 194-220)
      - Surrogate Parents, 1988 (Box 20)
      - Urban Affairs, 1987-1989 (Box 20)
      - Women's Commission (Michigan), 1987-1989; 3 folders (Box 20)
      - Women and Economics, 1986-1987 (Box 20)
      - Women and Pay Equity, 1985-1987 (Box 20)
  - William Liebold (Cabinet Secretary), 1985-1990
    The William Liebold subseries comprises over two linear feet of materials arranged alphabetically by type: cabinet, correspondence, and memoranda. The four folders of cabinet material are an extremely rich source on the meetings of Blanchard's executive committee and heads of departments. These were perhaps the most formal meetings between these high-ranking executives. The correspondence and memoranda provide a detailed record of Liebold's efforts to facilitate access to the governor.
    - Cabinet
      - Meetings, 1986-1990; 2 folders (Box 21)
      - International Affairs/Trade, 1989-1990; 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Correspondence
      - 1985-1988, 13 folders (Box 21)
      - 1989-1990, 7 folders (Box 22)
    - Memoranda
      - 1986-1988, 14 folders (Box 22)
      - 1989-1990, 9 folders (Box 23)
  - Carolyn Sparks (Executive Assistant), 1983-1990